{"tossups": [{"question": "The process of creating these places was paused after the article \"Dizzy From Success.\" The attempt to bring the entire countryside into these places resulted in the Holodomor and other episodes of famine, as well as direct killings of alleged \"kulaks.\" For 10 points, the First Five-Year Plan was aimed at transforming all Soviet agriculture into what socialist institutions?", "answer": "Soviet <b><u>collective farms</u></b> [or <b><u>sovkhoz</u></b>; or <b><u>kolkhoz</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer was patronized by Cardinal Rudolf of Austria, to whom he dedicated his <em>Archduke Trio</em>. This composer wrapped his head in pillows and hid in a basement during the Battle of Wagram, attempting to protect what little hearing he had left. For 10 points, name this composer of the <em>Pastoral</em> and <em>Choral</em> symphonies as well as \"Fur Elise.\"", "answer": "Ludwig van <b><u>Beethoven</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Following controversy over his proposed \"budget repair bill,\" this man defeated Tom Barrett for the second time in two years. An occupation of his state capitol occurred after he planned to outlaw bargaining with public unions, leading to a recall election which he survived in 2012. For 10 points, name this Republican governor of Wisconsin.", "answer": "Scott <b><u>Walker</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A politician controversially claimed that this place is not independent due to \"money and ethnic votes.\" This place was to be recognized as a \"distinct society\" in a failed 1987 amendment block, the Meech Lake Accord. This place rejected independence by a narrow margin in a 1995 referendum. For 10 points, name this French-speaking Canadian province.", "answer": "<b><u>Quebec</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A powerful advisor based in this city uncovered the Tavora (tuh-VORE-uh) Conspiracy. This city, where the Marquis of Pombal came to power, was the location of a 1755 disaster that inspired philosophers across Europe to ask how God could allow large-scale death. For 10 points, name this city that was devastated by a large earthquake described in <em>Candide</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Lisbon</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man ran for governor of Massachusetts in 1852 on the Free Soil ticket, and did not accept an offer to become president of Antioch College until the election returns confirmed his loss. He went on a tour of Prussia in 1843, six years after joining the U.S.'s first state board of education.  For 10 points, name this \"father of the common school,\" a leading educational reformer.", "answer": "Horace <b><u>Mann</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ship never fought a major battle, as it was under upgrades during Jutland (YUT-land). This ship was designed at the behest of First Sea Lord Jacky Fisher and targeted in a namesake \"hoax\" by Virginia Woolf, who pretended to be an Ethiopian princess. For 10 points, name this ship whose construction spurred a battleship \"arms race\" in the decade before World War I.", "answer": "<em>HMS</em> <em><b><u>Dreadnought</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This company helped put Butterfield's stagecoach line out of business despite operating for only eighteen months. It went as far west as Sacramento from its origin at St. Joseph, Missouri, and employed those who answered an ad for \"young, skinny, wiry fellows not over eighteen.\" For 10 points, name this 1860 to 1861 venture for delivering mail using a network of animals.", "answer": "<b><u>Pony Express</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, the preacher John Ball posed the riddle \u201cWhen Adam delve and Eve span, who was then the gentleman?\u201d This event ended shortly after William Walworth, the mayor of London, beheaded its leader. This event targeted Richard II and protested the recent poll tax. For 10 points, name this 1381 uprising in England led by Wat Tyler among a class of people.", "answer": "the <b><u>Peasants\u2019 Revolt</u></b> [or Wat <b><u>Tyler</u></b>\u2019s Revolt or Wat <b><u>Tyler</u></b>\u2019s Rebellion until \u201cWat Tyler\u201d is read; do not accept or prompt on \u201cPeasants\u2019 War\u201d]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "These people displaced an Iron Age culture known as the Villanovans. These people worshipped gods including Tin, Uni, and Cel, and they spoke a now-lost language whose last known speaker was the Roman emperor Claudius. They legendarily provided the final three kings of Rome. For 10 points, name these pre-Roman inhabitants of the central Italian peninsula.", "answer": "<b><u>Etruscan</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This country's Awash Valley is home to the city of Hadar, where Donald Johanson found the \"Lucy\" skeleton. This country lost its coastline in 1991 when the UNOVER mission conducted a referendum that secured independence for Eritrea. For 10 points, name this country which suffered a much-publicized 1980s famine and is governed from Addis Ababa.", "answer": "<b><u>Ethiopia</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man's two weeks fighting in the Confederate-affiliated Marion Rangers inspired his short story \"The Private History of a Campaign That Failed.\" With Charles Dudley Warner, he wrote a novel that gave its name to the post-Civil War period of prosperity in the North, <em>The Gilded Age</em>.  For 10 points, name this author who created Becky Thatcher, Huck Finn, and Tom Sawyer.", "answer": "Mark <b><u>Twain</u></b> [or Samuel Langhorne <b><u>Clemens</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "A major advance in this field was formulated by Stanley Jevons and William Marshall in the 1880s. This field's dominant textbook in postwar America was written by Paul Samuelson, who subscribed to the ideas formulated by John Maynard Keynes. For 10 points, name this social science which uses supply and demand curves to study financial decision-making.", "answer": "<b><u>economics</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "This country underwent a religious schism known as the \u201cRaskol\u201d when Patriarch Nikon attempted to change the number of fingers used to make the sign of the cross, leading to the split of the Old Believers. This country is home to the world\u2019s largest Eastern Orthodox population. For 10 points, name this home country of Kirill I, the Patriarch of Moscow.", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "In 1962, Henry Hammond Hess proposed that convection currents within this layer are the cause of seafloor spreading. In 1909, the boundary atop this layer was discovered by Andrija Mohorovic\u00edc (AHN-ree-huh moh-hoh-ROH-veech-itch). For 10 points, name this layer of the Earth which was hypothesized in the nineteenth century to lie between the core and crust.", "answer": "<b><u>mantle</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {}, {"question": "Two important models of this kind of device were introduced in 1976, Chuck Peddle\u2019s 6502 and Zilog\u2019s Z80. Those devices competed with the widely used 8080, from the company which manufactured influential later models of these devices such as the x86, Pentium series, and i7. For 10 points, name these devices at the heart of a computer, which are made by Intel.", "answer": "micro<b><u>processor</u></b>s [or <b><u>CPU</u></b>s; or <b><u>central processing unit</u></b>s]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {}, {"question": "This man and Benjamin Franklin are the only Americans honored as a \"Freeman of the City\" by St. Andrews. His victory at the American and British open and amateur tournaments gave him the 1930 grand slam. This man worked with Alister MacKenzie on his most lasting creation, in Augusta, Georgia. For 10 points, name this founder of the Masters golf tournament.", "answer": "Bobby <b><u>Jones</u></b> [Robert Tyre <b><u>Jones</u></b>, Jr.]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "A picket line formed by members of this profession got into a huge brawl with police at the Battle of Ogreave. Members of this profession who opposed the moderate NACODS joined the NUM led by Arthur Scargill. Members of this profession were dubbed \"the enemy within\" by Margaret Thatcher. For the point, identify this profession which launched a disastrous 1984 British strike which closed down facilities for extracting bitumen.", "answer": "<b><u>coal miner</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>miner</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This party nominated Atlantis crank Ignatius Donnelly for Vice-President in 1900, eight</u></b> <b><u>years after demanding the eight-hour workday and the direct election of Senators in the</u></b> <b><u>Omaha Platform. This party ran James (+)</u> Weaver for President in 1892 and, four years later, insisted on listing Thomas Watson as the running mate of the (*)</b> cross-listed Democratic nominee. For 10 points, name this party that peaked in 1896 by endorsing William Jennings Bryan.", "answer": "<b><u>Populist</u></b>s [or <b><u>People's</u></b> Party]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This bill specifically limited its scope to \"conventional military force\" in order to exclude</u></b> <b><u>nuclear strikes. This bill was put before the Senate in response to reported attacks on the</u></b> <em><b><u>Turner Joy</u> </b></em><b><u>and</u> </b><em><b><u>Maddox</u></b></em><b><u>. It was opposed by Ernest (+)</u> Gruening and Wayne Morse on the grounds of representing a (*)</b> conflict \"misguidedly drawn, which is steadily being escalated.\" For 10 points, name this August 1964 Congressional resolution authorizing Lyndon Johnson to conduct the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Gulf of Tonkin</u></b> Resolution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's colony fought Susquehannock Indians in the Peach War and granted</u></b> <b><u>religious freedom in the Flushing Remonstrance. Prior to England, this country sponsored</u></b> <b><u>the original American voyages of Henry (+)</u> Hudson. This country conquered the short-lived New Sweden colony in present-day Delaware, under the leadership of Peter (*) </b>Stuyvesant. For 10 points, name this country which originally colonized what is now New York.", "answer": "The <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> [or <b><u>Holland</u></b>; or the <b><u>Dutch Empire</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This art movement included a literary section in which poets Hugo Ball and Tristan</u></b> <b><u>Tzara worked. Artists in this movement produced \"ready-mades\" such as a bicycle (*)</u></b> <b>wheel and a urinal. This movement's name was supposedly chosen at the Cabaret Voltaire by sticking a (*) </b>pen-knife into a French dictionary at random. For 10 points, name this absurdist \"anti-art\" movement of the World War I era, which included Marcel Duchamp.", "answer": "<b><u>Dada</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man collaborated with Morris Halle on the 1968 phonological study</u> </b><em><b><u>The Sound</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Pattern of English</u></b></em><b><u>. That text extended his theory of \"poverty of the (+)</u> stimulus,\" or the inability of human culture to cause the development of (*)</b> language absent a biological role in the brain. For 10 points, name this theorist of transformational-generative grammar, an MIT linguist also known for his leadership of the intellectual left wing in the U.S.", "answer": "Noam <b><u>Chomsky</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's dictator Hilari\u00f3n Daza sparked a war by instituting a saltpeter tax,</u></b> <b><u>leading to this country losing its coastline in the Treaty of Anc\u00f3n. Both Butch Cassidy and</u></b> <b><u>Che Guevara were killed in this country, which lost southeastern territory to Paraguay in</u></b> <b><u>the (+)</u> Chaco War. This country, the site of the Potos\u00ed silver mine, is now led by (*)</b> coca enthusiast Evo Morales. For 10 points, identify this South American country named for the continent's \"liberator.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Bolivia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During a Senate debate which quickly turned into an argument about this crisis, Robert</u></b> <b><u>Hayne received the reply \"liberty and union, one and forever, now and inseparable\" from</u></b> <b><u>Daniel (+)</u> Webster. This crisis was exacerbated by the publication of the </b><em><b>South Carolina </b><b>Exposition and Protest</b></em><b>, and it led to the resignation of Vice-President (*)</b> John C. Calhoun. For 10 points, name this 1832 affair in which South Carolina asserted that it could block the Tariff of Abominations.", "answer": "<b><u>nullification</u></b> crisis", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2003, this person was identified as the \"Younger Queen\" mummy by the minority</u></b> <b><u>faction of archaeologists which holds that she was the same person as the pharaoh (+)</u></b> <b>Smenkhkare. Berlin's Neues (NOY-iss) Museum currently holds a famous (*)</b> bust of this person, which is traditionally attributed to a sculptor known as Thutmose. For 10 points, name this wife of Akhenaten who might have preceded Tutankhamun as pharaoh of Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Nefertiti</u></b>  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 9 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras </b> <b><u>This battle turned on the use of a perpendicular two-column approach, and the few losing</u></b> <b><u>ships that escaped were led by Federico Gravina. Prior to this battle, a (+)</u> semaphore message reading \"England expects that every man will do his duty\" was transmitted from the (*)</b><em>Victory</em>. For 10 points, name this 1805 naval battle at which Pierre-Charles Villeneuve was defeated by Horatio Nelson, who died during the fighting and is commemorated at a namesake London square.  ANSWER: Battle of <b><u>Trafalgar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}